Guide to the Nathan T. Porter, Jr. Collection of Bookplates by Edwin Davis French
Yale University Arts Library
Nathan T. Porter, Jr. Collection of Bookplates by Edwin Davis French
1893-1906
BKP 65
Yale University Arts Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
The collection comprises close to 200 bookplates designed by Edwin Davis French, which were collected by Nathan T. Porter, Jr.
Porter, Nathan T., 1867-1947
Associated Materials
See also the Pearson-Lowenhaupt Collection of Bookplates by Edwin Davis French (Call # BKP 49) and Edwin Davis French: A Memorial; His Life, His Art by Ira Hutchinson Brainerd, published in 1908 (Call # Bookplate Z996 F73 (LC)). In addition, several titles bearing the bookplate of Nathan T. Porter, Jr. can be found in the collections of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library and the Elizabethan Club.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011, it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Nathan Todd Porter, Jr. (1867-1947) was a dry goods commission merchant born in Brooklyn, NY. He graduated from Yale, Class of 1890. He worked for Porter Brothers & Co., located in New York, NY, and lived in Montclair, NJ. He married Caroline Chester Knickerbocker in 1892; they had two daughters: Helen and Caroline. He was also a member of the University Club and a trustee of the Montclair Free Public Library.
Edwin Davis French (1851-1906) was a designer and engraver born in North Attleboro, MA. In 1876 he moved to New York, NY, and he worked as a silver engraver and designer for Frank M. Whiting & Company until 1894. He also studied at the Art Students League. French became focused on copper engraving and designed his first bookplate in 1893. In 1897 he moved to Saranac Lake, NY, and he produced over 300 bookplate designs between 1893 and his death in 1906.
References:
Leonard, John W., ed. Who's Who in New York City and State. 3rd ed. New York: L. R. Hamersly & Company, 1907.
Brainerd, Ira Hutchinson. Edwin Davis French: A Memorial; His Life, His Art. New York: privately printed [De Vinne Press], 1908.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises close to 200 bookplates designed by Edwin Davis French, which were collected by Nathan T. Porter, Jr. In addition to bookplates, the collection also contains another example of engraved illustration by French, namely a small reproduction of Jean-François Millet's The Sower, which was used as the imprimatur of author and publisher William Loring Andrews.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates – Mounted. II. Bookplates – Unmounted. III. Other Engravings. IV. Ephemera.
Bookplates; Bookplates; French, Edwin Davis, 1851-1906; Porter, Nathan T., 1867-1947; Andrews, William Loring, 1837-1920
- Bookplates – Mounted, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains bookplates mounted on gray paper mounts, measuring 10 x 8 inches. The mounts are printed on recto with "No. _______" in the upper right corner and with "Collection of | Nathan T. Porter, Jr. | Montclair, N. J." in the lower left corner. The bookplate mounts are hand-numbered in black ink.
  Arrangement
  The bookplates are arranged in numerical order by their identification numbers from a published checklist of French's bookplates and other engravings, Edwin Davis French: A Memorial; His Life, His Art, by Ira Hutchinson Brainerd (1908). According to Brainerd, the checklist "follows [French's] notation with the little continuation needed to carry it to completion." This arrangement is roughly chronological, although some earlier bookplates have been appended to the end of Brainerd's checklist (see Box 2, Folder 10).
  - No. 1b (Brainerd) – No. 31 (Warner), 1893-1894; 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - No. 1b Helen Elvira Brainerd, 1893
    - No. 2b Mary Brainerd French, 1893
    - No. 4 Helen Elvira Brainerd, 1893
    - No. 5c E D F (Edwin Davis French), 1893
    - No. 8 Charles E. Clark, M.D., 1894; 2 copies
    - No. 9 Charles E. Clark, M.D., 1894
    - No. 10c In Memoriam. Ellen Walters Avery, 1894
    - No. 11 William Loring Andrews, 1894
    - No. 12 The Oxford Club, 1894
    - No. 15 Marshall Clifford Lefferts, 1894
    - No. 18c Colonial Dames of America, 1894
    - No. 19b Charles B. Foote, 1894
    - No. 22b Hiram Edmund Deats, 1894
    - No. 25b Alice C. Holden, 1894
    - No. 26 Edwin R. Holden, 1894
    - No. 27c John Page Woodbury, 1894
    - No. 28b Richard B. Coutant, 1894
    - No. 30b Francis Goodwin, 1894
    - No. 31 Beverley Warner, M.A., 1894
  - No. 33a (Kalbfleisch) – No. 58c (Marshall), 1894-1895; 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - No. 33a Charles Conover Kalbfleisch, 1894
    - No. 34b Henry Sherburne Rowe, 1894
    - No. 35 Emily Hoe Lawrence, 1894; 2
    - No. 36b James Hale Bates, 1894
    - No. 37c Richard Southcote Mansergh, 1895
    - No. 40d Library of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1895
    - No. 41b E. D. Church, 1895
    - No. 42 A. C. Bernheim, 1895
    - No. 44 Charles B. Alexander, 1895
    - No. 46 James William Ellsworth, 1895
    - No. 47 Beverly Chew, 1895
    - No. 48b Henry H. Vail, 1895
    - No. 49 Thomas Jefferson McKee, 1895
    - No. 51 Micajah P. Clough, 1895
    - No. 52 Henry A. Sherwin, 1895
    - No. 54b Mariæ Gerard Messenger, 1895
    - No. 55 William Frederick Havemeyer, 1895
    - No. 56 Theo. L. DeVinne, 1895
    - No. 58c Frank Evans Marshall, 1895
  - No. 59 (Champaign Public Library) – No. 92 (McCarter), 1895-1897; 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - No. 59 Champaign Public Library, 1895
    - No. 60b Biltmoris G W V (George W. Vanderbilt), 1895
    - No. 65 William Lanman Bull, 1895
    - No. 66 Micajah Pratt Clough, 1896
    - No. 67 The Association of the Bar of the City of New York | The Library of Charles H. Woodbury, 1895
    - No. 73 Christian Archibald Herter, 1896
    - No. 74b A. J. Morgan, 1896
    - No. 75b Howard Willets, 1896
    - No. 76c Presented to _____, Esqr. With the Compliments of William Loring Andrews, 1896
    - No. 77b Robert Sedgwick, 1896
    - No. 82 Henry A. Sherwin, 1896
    - No. 83b The John Crerar Library, 1896
    - No. 83c The John Crerar Library | Chicago, 1896
    - No. 84c The Denver Club, 1896
    - No. 86b Maria Gerard Messenger, 1896
    - No. 86d Maria Gerard Messenger, 1896
    - No. 86e Maria Gerard Messenger, 1896
    - No. 88 The Collection of Thos. Addis Emmet, M.D., 1896
    - No. 90 O. A. K. (O. A. Kahn), 1897
    - No. 91 Lucy Coleman Carnegie, 1897
    - No. 92 Robert H. McCarter, 1896
  - No. 93 (Stearns) – No. 125 (Cox), 1897-1898 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - No. 93 John Lloyd Stearns, 1897
    - No. 94b Edith Davies Kingsbury, 1897
    - No. 98 Authors Club Library, 1897
    - No. 99b Ruth Mary Sabin, undated
    - No. 101c The Mark Skinner Library | Manchester, Vermont, 1898
    - No. 102c Paul Lemperly, 1897
    - No. 103 Henry Clay and Helen Burgess Ranney, 1897
    - No. 104b Edward F. Burke, 1897
    - No. 108 Library of Princeton University, 1897
    - No. 112 A. Dwight Stratton, 1898
    - No. 113 Samuel W. Lambert, 1898
    - No. 114b Barrett Wendell, 1898
    - No. 115 Ex Libris Medicis, 1898
    - No. 116 Vassar Alumnæ Historical Association, 1898
    - No. 118 The Association of the Bar of the City of New York | The John E. Burrill Fund, 1897
    - No. 119b The Association of the Bar of the City of New York | Gift of James C. Carter, 1898
    - No. 121 James A. Goldsmith, 1898
    - No. 122a Twentieth Century Club | Ex Dono, 1898
    - No. 122b Twentieth Century Club, 1898
    - No. 125 Jennings Stockton Cox, 1898
  - No. 127a (Thorne) – No. 152 (Treadwell Library), 1898-1899; 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - No. 127a Katherine Cecil Sanford Thorne, 1898
    - No. 129 James Edmund Scripps, 1898
    - No. 130 Arnold Wood, 1898
    - No. 131 Charles L. Dana, 1898
    - No. 132 Eva Snow Smith Prescott, 1898
    - No. 133b Sidney Ernest Bradshaw, 1898
    - No. 135 John F. Talmage, 1899
    - No. 136b Edward Courtland Gale, 1899
    - No. 137b Ethel Hartshorne Wood, 1899
    - No. 139 Emil Leopold Boas, 1899
    - No. 140a Louise Taylor Hartshorne Moore, 1899
    - No. 141d Charles Dexter Allen, 1899
    - No. 142 Allan C. Bakewell, 1899
    - No. 143a George Van Wagenen and Margaret Van Nest Duryee, 1899
    - No. 144 A W (Arnold Wood), 1899
    - No. 146 John Skelton Williams, 1899
    - No. 149b Cornelia Horsford, 1899
    - No. 152 Treadwell Library | Massachusetts General Hospital, 1899
  - No. 153 (Lemperly) – No. 179 (Sherman), 1900-1901; 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 153 ... The Property of Paul Lemperly, 1900
    - No. 154 The University Club | Cleveland, 1900
    - No. 155 Robert Emmet Hopkins, 1900
      General note
      Bookplate is inscribed "E-D French to J. W. Pinger [?], Esq."
    - No. 157f The Union League Club | New York, 1900; 2 copies
    - No. 159 John R. Livermore, 1900
    - No. 163c New York Yacht Club Library, 1900
    - No. 163d New York Yacht Club Library | Presented By, 1900
    - No. 163db New York Yacht Club Library | Presented By, 1900
    - No. 164b Walter B. James, M.D., 1900
    - No. 168 Margaret H. Foot, 1900
    - No. 169 John W. and Lee Partridge Loveland, 1900
    - No. 170 Amy B. Alexander, 1900
    - No. 171b James Wilson Bullock, 1900
    - No. 172 Arthur West Little, 1900
    - No. 173 John B. Larner, 1900
    - No. 174 Ruth Adams, 1900
    - No. 177 S. Walter Woodward, 1901
    - No. 178 Sarah Elizabeth Whitin, 1901
    - No. 179 William Watts Sherman, 1901
  - No. 180 (Barnes) – No. 213 (Burnham), 1901-1902; 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - No. 180 John Sanford Barnes, 1901
    - No. 182 The Worcester Art Museum, 1901
    - No. 184 Harbor Hill, 1901
    - No. 186c Library of the Harvard Union, 1901
    - No. 187 Frances Amelia Adams, 1901
    - No. 188d Roger Bigelow Merriman, 1901
    - No. 192b Long Island Historical Society | Storrs Memorial Fund, 1901
    - No. 194 Field Memorial Library | Conway, Massachusetts, 1901
    - No. 196 James M. Varnum, 1902
    - No. 197b James B. Dill, 1902
    - No. 198 Dorothy Furman, 1902
    - No. 199 Edward Dean Adams, 1902
    - No. 204b R. Stockton Pyne, 1902
    - No. 205b William Beverley Rogers, 1902
    - No. 206b The Washington County Free Library | Hagerstown, Maryland, 1902
    - No. 207b Ernest Kempton Adams, 1902
    - No. 212b Ira Hutchinson Brainerd, 1902
    - No. 213 William Henry and Katharine French Burnham, 1902
  - No. 217b (Mynderse) – No. 245b (Lovett), 1903-1904; 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - No. 217b Wilhelmus Mynderse, 1903
    - No. 218 L M P (Lowell Mason Palmer), 1903
    - No. 219 L M P (Lowell Mason Palmer), 1903
    - No. 222b W C W (W. C. Wood), 1903
    - No. 224b Ruth Lancaster Hoe, 1903
    - No. 225 Charles Williston McAlpin, 1903
    - No. 228b William Augustus Brewer, 1903
    - No. 229 Warner Mifflin and Louise Hartshorne Leeds, 1903
    - No. 231 Caroline Seagrave Bliss, 1903
    - No. 233 Elizabeth Sage Goodwin, 1903
    - No. 234 Cincinnati Law Library | Rufus King Fund, 1903
    - No. 235a Lowell Melvin Palmer, 1904
    - No. 237a Mary Barber Robinson, 1904
    - No. 240a Library of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1904
    - No. 240e Library of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers | The Gift Of, 1904
    - No. 241b Mabel Slade, 1904
    - No. 242 Henry C. Bernheim, 1904
    - No. 243 Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1904
    - No. 244 George Edward Dimock, 1904
    - No. 245b Benjamin Barnes Lovett, 1904
  - No. 248 (Hoffman) – No. 282b (Utica Public Library), 1904-1906; 20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - No. 248 Samuel Verplanck Hoffman, 1904
    - No. 249 Henry H. Harper, 1904
    - No. 254 John Notman, 1904
    - No. 256 Gertrude Clarkson Welsh, 1904
    - No. 259b Harriette M. Stevens, 1905
    - No. 260 Mary Lois Seagrave Downes, 1905
    - No. 263 Queen's University, 1905
    - No. 264b George Harvey, 1905
    - No. 265b Lucius G. Fisher, 1905
    - No. 269 George J. Gould | Georgian Court, 1906
    - No. 270 Parke E. Simmons, 1906
    - No. 271b Henry Van Deventer Black, 1906
    - No. 272 Elizabeth Jordan, 1906
    - No. 273 The Cosmos Club, 1906
    - No. 274 Emma Stewart Bixby, 1906
    - No. 275c W K Bixby, 1906
    - No. 276b Julius C. and Emily S. Bernheim, 1906
    - No. 278 L H J and S E J (Jackman), 1906
    - No. 281 Esther Pierce Metcalf, 1906
    - No. 282b Utica Public Library | From the John E. Brandegee Fund, 1906
  - No. 286 (Smith) – No. 289d (Tatlock), 1893 1898; 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - No. 286 Henry A. Smith, 1898
    - No. 289b Edwin Davis French, 1893
    - No. 289c William and Helen Woodruff Tatlock, 1893
    - No. 289d William Tatlock, 1893
- Bookplates – Unmounted, Series II
  This series contains unmounted bookplates which were loosely inserted among the mounted bookplates.
  These bookplates are unnumbered, although their arrangement follows that of the numerical order of the checklist published in 1908. According to Brainerd, the checklist "follows [French's] notation with the little continuation needed to carry it to completion." This arrangement is roughly chronological, although some earlier bookplates have been appended to the end of Brainerd's checklist.
  - No. 5d (French) – No. 296 (U-sepe-ars-so-ap), 1893-1905; 12 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - No. 5d E D F (Edwin Davis French), 1893
    - No. 20 Henry Blackwell, 1894
    - No. 72c The Edward Tompkins McLaughlin Memorial Prize in English Composition, 1896
    - No. 96cc Helen Keyes, 1897
    - No. 96h Eveline Warner Brainerd, 1897
    - No. 100 Child Memorial Library | To Harvard University | In Memory of Francis James Child, 1897
    - No. 130 Arnold Wood, 1898
    - No. 160 Nathan T. Porter, Jr., 1900; 2 copies
    - No. 163d New York Yacht Club Library, 1900
    - No. 261a Ethel Hartshorne Wood, 1905
    - No. 294 Martha Elizabeth Brainerd, 1905
    - No. 296 U-sepe-ars-so-ap, 1893
- Other Engravings, Series III
  - The Sower, 1894; 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    This folder contains an unsigned engraving by French that is a small reproduction of Jean-François Millet's The Sower, which was used as the imprimatur of William Loring Andrews.
- Ephemera, Series IV
  - Unused bookplate mounts, undated; 23 items (Box 2, Folder 13)